（アナ）バーベキュー　うま～っ！
This barbecue's so good!
（キュービック）ギャモン　焼けたよ。
（ギャモン）おう。
Yours is ready, Gammon.
Thanks.
（ソウジ）たくさんあるから
どんどん食べてね。
There's a lot, so eat up.
（ノノハ）もう　分かんない！
（せき込む音）
I don't understand.
I just don't understand!
私　わけ分かんない！　私たち　今
愚者のパズルの中にいるんですよね。
This is a Fools' Puzzle, right?
そうだけど　何が
わけ分からないの？
Yes, that's correct. What is it that you don't understand?
The part about us having a barbecue in the middle of a Fools' Puzzle.
愚者のパズルで
バーベキューやるって神経です！
腹が減っては
戦はできないからね。
You can't fight on an empty stomach.
パンで　いいじゃん。　お菓子で
いいじゃん。　バーベキューって！
Some bread or snacks would be fine, but a barbecue?!
殺人パズルの中で
よく　まあ　のんきに…。
Why are we having a carefree barbecue while we're solving a deadly puzzle?
（ギャモン）ノノハ　肉　焼けてんぞ。
そっちは　どうだ？　カイト。　ギブか？
Nonoha, the meat's roasted.
How about you, Kaito?
Do you give up?
８本のバーベキューを　縦４本　横４本
組み合わせて並べる。
Organize the meat on the eight skewers into a 4x4 grid.
そのとき　肉が重なったら
不正解だ。
The meat can't overlap.
刺さっている肉を　動かすような
マネ　すんじゃねえぞ。
I hope you're not trying to move the meat on the skewers!
Shut up! You told me already!
（カイト）さっき聞いたよ。
うっせ～な！
肉が焼けんの
待ってただけだっつ～の。
I was just waiting for the meat to roast!
よし　解けた。
食べ物で遊ばない。　パズルにしない！
Solved!
Stop playing with your food! And don't make puzzles out of it!
（キュービック）ねえねえ　カイト！
（２人）あっ？！
Hey, Kaito!
骨を１本　動かして
正しい数式にしてみてよ！
Move one bone to make the equation correct!
キューちゃんも　マネしない！
ソーセージの立体パズル～。
Don't follow his bad example, Cubie!
Look, a 3D puzzle made out of sausages!
あ～！
あんたら　バカなの？！
Are you guys retarded?!
Is "genius" a synonym for "stupid"?
天才って　バカの代名詞なの？！
まあまあ　ＰＯＧとの戦いも
終わったことだし→
Well, the fight with the POG is over,
これからは　明るく　楽しく
愚者のパズルを解こうよ。
so let's just have fun by cheerfully solving Fools' Puzzles!
It's not fun or cheerful!
明るくないし　楽しくないし！
う～！
何　カリカリしてんだ？　ノノハ。
さっきから　うるせえぞ。
Why are you so on edge, Nonoha?
It's getting annoying.
（ギャモン・カイト）うわ～！
あんたら～！　う～！
You dumb-asses!
Don't step here, it's a trap!
(That means you, Nonoha!)
あれ？
（２人）あ～！
Huh?
バカか　お前は？！　愚者のパズルで
はしゃぐんじゃねえ！
Are you crazy?! Don't be so careless in a Fool's Puzzle!
バカに　バカって
言われたくないわ！
Look who's talking!
Look who's talking about who's talking!
バカに「バカにバカって言われたく
ないわ！」って言われたくないわ！
lost te saguri de sagashiteta
Lost, trying to find it blindly with my hands.
tozasareta mirai no kotae nante doko ni mo nai
But the key to the locked future is nowhere to be found.
hashiru shoudou ima kaidoku funou
Undecipherable urges surging.
found kudaketa hazu no unmei wo
I found the fate I believed broken.
mijukuna yume no naka de kikoetekitan da
I heard it in my immature dream.
saigo made I'll be there for you
I'll be there for you till the very end.
tachitomaranai kono hari dake wa
I can't stop. I hear nothing else.
boku no asu wo kizamu oto tsukisasu
How this needle carves my future.
shinjitsu kara nigetara ima
I'm running away from the truth now.
genjitsu ni mo maketara ima
I'm losing to reality now.
nani ga nokoru no (nokoru no)
What will be left?
kazoekirenai kono kizu dake ga
The countless scars on my body
boku no kinou wo zanzou toshite kataru
are the only thing telling the story of my past.
unmei ga hodokete mo ima
Even if fate falls apart now,
sonzai wo kowashite mo ima
even if existence shatters now,
boku no michi wo yuku yo
I'm walkng down my own path.
It's now or never.
This is what they say: "Live your life today."
There will always be, there will always be a way.
The Orpheus Order
（バロン）そうですか。　分かりました。
気をつけて　帰ってきてください。
I see. I understand.
Please be careful on your way back.
（バロン）軸川君からです。
That was Jikugawa.
また一つ　カイト君たちが
愚者のパズルを解放してくれました。
Kaito and his friends have released another Fools' Puzzle.
（フンガ）彼らには感謝ですね。
We should be thankful for that.
They're helping us clean up this mess and rebuild the POG from scratch.
負の遺産を一掃して
出直さんとするＰＯＧとしては。
（バロン）全てが終わり
平和な日々が　よみがえった…。
It's all over. Our peaceful days have returned.
あとは…　お前の記憶さえ
戻ってくれれば…。
Now if only your memories would return too...
ジン…　今夜は　ゆっくり
チェスでもやろうか…。
Jin.
Shall we play a friendly chess game tonight?
やっぱ　分かんないなぁ　私。
何が？
I really don't get it.
Get what?
カイトが　まだ愚者のパズルに
挑戦する理由。
The reason why you're still challenging Fools' Puzzles.
「人殺しのパズルは　全部　俺が潰す」
ってだけじゃないでしょ？
It's more than just crushing murderous puzzles, isn't it?
ジンと約束したからな。
出会ったパズルは　必ず解くって。
I promised Jin
that I'll solve every puzzle I come across.
約束は守んなきゃな。
ふ～ん。　あっ　そう。
That's a promise I have to keep.
Oh, really?
But you didn't keep your promise to me.
カイト　私との約束
守らなかったわよね？　覚えてる？
Do you remember?
覚えてる。　オルペウス島へ行くとき。
悪かった…。
I do. When I left for Orpheus Tower...
Sorry about that.
あぁ。　やだ　もう。
そんなマジで　取んないでよ。
Oh, don't worry about it.
別に大したことじゃないし。
ちょっと言ってみただけだよ。
It's not a big deal.
You just went there.
大したことじゃなくねえ。
あっ？！　カイト？
It is a big deal.
Kaito?
あの時だって…　あの日…
ルークと会った最後の日…。
That time... That day when I last saw Rook...
俺は　解きかけのパズルに
夢中になっちまって→
I was absorbed in a puzzle I was doing,
約束の時間に遅刻した。
and I ended up being late to the meeting.
そのせいで　いつもより
帰るのが遅くなって→
Because of that, we ended up staying later than usual,
ルークの居ないのに気づいたやつらが
ルークを…。
and those men came for Rook after they had realized he was missing.
俺が約束を守っていれば…。
If I had kept my promise...
カイト…　終わったことだよ。
Kaito, that's in the past now.
ルーク君も　ＰＯＧも　元に戻って…
もう全部　終わったこと…　ねぇ。
Rook and the POG are back to normal.
It's all over now.
Right?
Yeah.
（フリーセル）ママ…　いよいよ始まるよ。
Nana, it's finally time.
あしたから　カイトと遊ぶんだ。
I'll be playing with Kaito starting tomorrow.
楽しみだよ…　ママ…。
I'm really looking forward to it.
ああぁ　ひどい渋滞。
This traffic is awful.
（アイリ）
生徒と先生も　遅刻確実ですね。
Both the students and teachers will be late.
あ～ん　事故でもあったのか？
（タマキ）はぁ…　ショックだわ…。
Was there an accident or something?
This is such a shame.
入学以来
無遅刻　無欠席だったのに…。
Ever since I entered this school, I've never been late or missed a single class.
生徒会　副会長として失格…。
I'm a failure as the vice president of the student council.
It's no biggie!
んな大した事じゃねえじゃん。
俺なんか　しょっちゅうだぜ。
Happens to me all the time!
君と一緒にしないで！
Don't put me in the same league as you!
生徒会長の信頼を
失っちゃうかもしれないのよ　私。
I may end up losing the president's trust!
軸川先輩は　遅刻ぐらいで
怒ったりしませんよ。
Jikugawa wouldn't get mad at you just for being late.
それは　そうだけど…　私的には。
That's true, but for me it's still...
メール？
ああ。　軸川先輩からだ。
A text?
Yeah.
It's from Jikugawa.
（キュービック）あっ！　カイト。
（アナ）カイト～！
Ah, Kaito!
Kaito!
呼び出して悪かったね。
会長。　この渋滞は　一体？
Sorry for calling you here like this.
President, what's with this traffic?
こいつは？！
What's this?
（タマキ）キープアウト　立ち入り禁止。
なんで？！
"Keep out"? It's off limits? Why?
Hey! Isn't the POG supposed to be back to normal?!
おい！　ＰＯＧは　元に
戻ったんじゃなかったのかよ！
Huh?
えっ？！
こんな　くだらねえマネ
するやつは　他にいねえ！
Who else would do something stupid like this?
何　たくらんでる？！
違う。　我々ではない。
What's the big plan now?!
You're wrong. It's not us.
招待されたのは　君。
だから　君を呼んだ。
They summoned you. That's why I called you.
招待？
千枝乃君。
（タマキ）はい。
An invitation?
Chieno.
Yes?
君にしかできない
お願いがあるんだけど。
I have a task that only you can do.
（タマキ）何でしょうか？
速やかに　スクールバスをＵターンさせ→
What is it?
Make all the school buses turn around,
生徒は　自宅待機するよう
伝えてくれないかな？
and tell the students to return home.
えっ？！　私１人で　ですか？！
ごめんね。
Me alone?
Sorry.
分かりました。
Okay.
どうする？　カイト君。
What are you going to do, Kaito?
Kaito!
（アナ・キュービック）カイト。
えっ？　なに　なに？
What's happening?
Kaito!
カイト！
カイト君！
Kaito!
のわ～！　とっ　とっ　とっ。
ざけんなよぉ…。
Don't give me this shit!
カイト君！
Kaito!
な　何なのよ　これ…。
What's going on?
隠し文字。
えっ？！
Hidden letters.
If you look at the hidden letters, it says "Kaito in."
このテープに隠された文字を
並べると　「ＫＡＩＴＯＩＮ」。
あぁ！　これが　招待状？
That's the invitation?
何者の仕業なんだ…
何の目的で　カイト君を…。
Whose doing is this?
Why did they call Kaito?
We can't go after him with the bridge like this.
（キュービック）あとを追おうにも
橋が　これじゃ。
まだ　方法はある。
There's another way.
（ギャモン）ああ！　参った参った。
寝坊しちまったぜ。
Crap, I overslept.
あっ？！　あれは…。
Huh? It's...
よう！　どこ行くんだ？
そんなに急いで。
Hey! Where are you guys off to in such a hurry?
Follow us, Gammon!
ギャモン君も　来なさ～い！
Huh? Uh, roger!
（ギャモン）ん？　は　はいっ！
心の声
どこの誰だか知らねえが
ふざけやがって！
I don't know who did this crap,
心の声
探し出して　ぶっ飛ばしてやる！
but I'll find them and teach them a lesson!
何だ　こりゃ？！
What the hell is that?!
たった一晩で　こんなバカでっかい
もんが　学園に…？！
How did something this huge pop up on campus overnight?
This... Don't tell me...
こ　これは…　もしかして…。
What... is that?
何　あれ…？
It could be a puzzle.
もしかしたら　パズルかも…。
Yeah. And quite a tough one too.
だな。　しかも　かなり
ヤバそうだぜ。
If it's not the POG, who else would make a puzzle like that?
パズルって　ＰＯＧじゃないなら
一体　誰が　あんなものを？
それを知るためにも
カイト君が心配だ。　急ごう。
We should try to find out.
I'm worried about Kaito. We should hurry.
はい。
Yeah.
鏡を使った隠し文字…
心の声
間違いねぇ。
Letters hidden behind mirrors.
This is definitely a puzzle!
これは　パズルだ。
心の声
むかつくんだよ　やり口が…。
The way they do it pisses me off.
いいぜ！　この挑戦　受けてやる！
Very well! I accept your challenge!
It's puzzle time!
パズルタイムの始まりだ！
どこだ？　パズルは！
Where's the puzzle?
何？　ああっ　ガラスが壁に…。
What?
The glass turned into walls?
おい！　こいつは
どんなパズルだってんだよ？！
What kind of a puzzle is this?!
Ope-
開け…　おっ？！　はっ。
心の声
ガラスが　スモークになったり
鏡になったり…　一体　何なんだ…。
The glass turned opaque and then into a mirror.
What's going on?
ようこそ！　裁きのパズルへ…。
Welcome to the puzzle of judgment.
お前は…　きのう
愚者のパズルにいた…。
You're...
that guy from the Fools' Puzzle yesterday!
何もんだ？！　俺に　何の用だ？！
Who are you? What do you want from me?
今から　ここに　パズルが現れる。
A puzzle will appear here soon.
Yes, one of the murderous puzzles which you despise.
そう…。
君が憎む　人殺しのパズルがね…。
この空間は　君を囲んでいる
ガラスと同じ→
This room is a maze made from that special glass that surrounds you.
特殊ガラスで　できた迷路だ。
[TEL]
くそっ…。
Damn!
（フリーセル）中央の星マークが　君だ。
ルートは　４つ。
The star in the middle is you.
There are four routes,
ただし　正解は　１つだけ。
間違えれば　この空間は崩壊する。
but only one is the correct answer.
If you choose the wrong one, this room will collapse.
これから　僕が　正解ルートで
出口へ向かうから→
I will follow the correct path to the exit now,
君も　同じルートを使って
脱出すればいい。
so you should do the same.
ヒントは　鏡に映る僕の姿。
The hint is my reflection in the mirror.
ただし　さっきも言ったように
このガラスは　スモークになったり→
As you noticed earlier, the glass can change from mirror to opaque to transparent and vice versa.
鏡になったりするからね。
僕が出口を出てから　１分以内に
出られないと　君　死ぬよ。
If you can't escape within a minute after me,
you'll die.
…っざけんじゃねえぞ。　人殺しの
パズルなんかに　俺は負けねえ！
Kiss my ass. I won't lose to a murderous puzzle!
解いてやる。
解いて　てめえを　ぶん殴る！
I'll solve it for you.
I'll solve it and smash your face in!
うふ　じゃあ　頑張ろうよ。
Good luck then.
レッツ・プレイ・アップ。
Let's play up!
（フリーセル）僕は　出口まで　１ブロックずつ
３回移動する。
I will move block by block towards the exit in three moves.
君が　答えを言った瞬間に
君の周りのガラスは　開くよ。
The moment you say the correct answer, the glass walls around you will open,
but you need to figure out which way you're looking first.
でも　まずは　君自身が　どっちを
向いてるかを見つけないとね。
心の声
鏡だけなら　まだしも
ガラスになったり　スモークになったり…。
If it were mirrors only, it would be easy,
but with it changing from mirror to opaque...
心の声
膨大な鏡と
ガラスの組み合わせの中から→
I need to find the correct answer in this maze of glass and mirrors?
心の声
たった一つの答えを
見つけろってのか…。
心の声
こいつは　超難解だぜ…。
Damn, this is a tough one.
What is this? Where's the president?
何なの？　これ…。　会長は？！
（ピノクル）
千枝乃タマキは　軸川ソウジが好き。
Chieno Tamaki loves Jikugawa Souji.
お困りのようですね…　お嬢様…。
You look troubled, young lady.
はっ！　誰？！
でも　彼は　大門カイトに夢中。
Who're you?
But he's obsessed with Daimon Kaito.
あなたを見てもくれない。
かわいそうな千枝乃タマキさん。
He won't even look at you. Poor little Chieno Tamaki.
ハハハッ…　大門カイトなんて
居なくなれば　いいのにね…。
If only Daimon Kaito was no more...
心の声
落ち着け。
まずは情報を整理するんだ。
Calm down. Sort out the information first.
心の声
俺の前に　やつは　居ねえ。
He is not in front of me.
心の声
見えるのは　右。　左に２人。
There is one of him on the right and two on the left.
心の声
右後ろに　１人と
左後ろに　３人…。
One behind me on the right and three behind me on the left.
心の声
もっと絞り込むんだ。
I have to narrow it down.
This maze is made of squares and their diagonals.
心の声
この迷路は　正方形と
その対角線を結ぶ壁でできている。
心の声
ならば　迷路に沿って　直線で進む
光の入射角と反射角は　４５度→
In that case, the angle of incidence and reflection
of a ray of light going straight are both 45 degrees, so 90 degrees total.
心の声
合わせて　９０度。
直角に曲がることになる。
They turn in angles.
心の声
迷路を直線的に捉えるんだ。
I'm perceiving the maze in a straight line.
心の声
余計なものに惑わされるな。
I mustn't be misled by excess information.
心の声
真後ろと　真横から来た
映像だけを見るんだ。
I should only consider the reflections from behind and from my sides.
心の声
９０度の反射で届く光は
俺の周りの３方向から来ている。
The light is reflected at me in right angles from three directions.
心の声
やつは　３ブロックの移動で
出口へたどりつく場所にいるから→
He is in a place where he can reach the exit in three moves.
心の声
この４つのうちの　どれか。
From these four, which is it?
If the exit was A, I could never see three reflections.
心の声
出口をＡとした場合　どうやっても
３人の映像にはならない。
心の声
つまり　Ａの出口は　正解じゃねえ。
Which means A is not the correct answer.
心の声
Ｂの場合　可能…。
なら　Ｃは…　可能…。
In B's case, it's possible.
And C? That's possible too.
心の声
Ｄなら…　これも可能。
It's possible for D as well.
（フリーセル）フン。　苦戦してるね。
You're having trouble.
がっかりだな！　ファイ・ブレイン。
What a disappointment, Phi Brain.
いや　ファイ・ブレインを拒否した者
大門カイト。
Rather, the one who rejected the Phi Brain, Daimon Kaito.
どうして　それを？！　あはっ。
Why do you know that?
ずっと見てたよ。
君と親友との戦い。
We enjoyed your fight with your friend.
結構　楽しかった。
It was a battle on par with the fight between Count Pythagoras and Makata Jin.
ピタゴラス伯爵と真方ジンの戦いに
匹敵する名勝負だったね。
うっ…　そんなことまで…。
You know about that too?!
当然知ってるさ。　神の書に　お目に
かかれる　唯一のチャンスなんだから。
Of course I do.
It was our only chance to catch a glimpse of the Divine Revelations.
Who the hell-
てめえは　一体…？！
カイト…　君は　人を傷つけるパズルを
憎んでいるけど　それは　きれい事。
Kaito, you claim to hate puzzles that hurt people,
but that's just a false pretense.
君だって　人を
傷つけてきたじゃないか。
Did you not hurt people along the way?
なんだと？！
What?
You broke your promises without hesitation
そう。　平然と約束を破り
友を傷つけても　何とも思わない。
and didn't care for how much you hurt your friends.
しょせん　独りぼっちだよね。
カイトは。
You've always been a lone wolf, Kaito.
君にあげるヒントは　ここまでだよ。
These are all the hints I can give you.
ラスト１回の移動を
見ることはできない。
I can't show you the last move.
さあ　残り１分で
そこから脱出してみせてよ。
You now have one minute to find the way out.
負けねえ！…　俺は約束したんだ。
すべてのパズルは　俺が解くって！
I won't lose.
I promised I'd solve all the puzzles!
Kaito's brain is speeding up!
カイトの脳が活性化してる！
活性化？
Speeding up?
これは…　オルペウスの腕輪を
付けてた時と　そっくりだ！
It's the same as when he had the Armband of Orpheus.
心の声
直角に曲がる光によって
得られる情報を抽出することで→
I should be able to figure out his position
心の声
やつの位置は　割り出せるはずだ。
from the rays of light turning at right angles.
心の声
スタート地点で見えたのは　３方向。
At first, three directions were possible.
右　左　後ろ。
心の声
Right, left and back.
これにより　Ａのルートは除外された。
I can exclude A.
心の声
次の移動で現れたのは
右と左の２方向。
Next, he appeared twice on the left and the right.
心の声
これに当てはまるのが
Ｂと…　Ｃ
。
B and C matches this... and so does D.
心の声
Ｄもか。
With the third move, he appeared twice on the left and the right again.
心の声
３度目に見えたのも
右と左の２方向。
心の声
これを再現できるのは…
Ｂのルートは可能。
This is possible from route B, C and D.
心の声
Ｃのルートも可能。
Ｄのルートでも可能。
心の声
どれでも　ありうる。
All three are possible.
心の声
どれだ？
この３つのうちの　どれが？
Which one of the three is it?
Which one?
心の声
何が違う？　何が…。
What's different? What?
この３つのルートの違い。
心の声
何が…。
How are the three routes different?
回想
しょせん独りぼっちだよね　カイトは。
You've always been a lone wolf, Kaito.
あぁ　そうか！
I see! It's the distance!
距離だ！　最後に見たやつの姿が
俺から　５ブロック先。
With the last move, he was five blocks away from me.
そして　その反対側に見えたやつの
姿は　それより近い　３ブロック先。
Then he was closer behind me, three blocks away.
In B's case, the light would pass 3 and 9 blocks to reach me.
Ｂのルートの場合　俺に届く光は
３ブロックと　９ブロック先！
Ｄのルートの場合は
１１ブロック先と　５ブロック先の光！
In D's case, it would be 11 and 5 blocks.
In C's case, it's 3 and 5 blocks!
Ｃのルートを進む光なら　３ブロック先と
５ブロック先の光が　俺に届く！
つまり…　正解は
俺の真後ろにある　出口Ｃだ！
Which means...
The correct answer is exit C!
カイト～！
Kaito!
カイト！
That was close.
あっぶねえ！
危機一髪だったね。
Yeah, too close.
カイト！　キューちゃん。
助かったよ。　寿命が縮んだぜ。
Kaito! Cubie!
Thanks! I think that took a few days off my lifespan.
軸川先輩の案内で
非常用の裏門から入ったの。
Jikugawa led us in through the rear emergency exit.
やっぱり　カイトは
僕が居なくちゃ　ダメだね。
You're totally hopeless without me around.
エヘヘッ！　こいつ！
You rascal!
≫（フリーセル）ギリギリだったね　カイト。
That was close, Kaito.
オルペウスの腕輪なしで解いたことは
褒めてあげる。
I applaud you for solving it without the Armband of Orpheus.
でも…　この程度じゃ
僕らの計画の役には立たないなぁ。
But at this level, you'd be of no use to our plan.
（ギャモン）何だ？　てめえは？
Who the hell are you?!
カイト。
Kaito!
これから君は　信じていた者に
次々と裏切られ　ゲームを挑まれる。
From now on, you will be betrayed by those you trust one after another,
and you will face the game's challenges.
なにっ！
でも　それは　当然の報い。
What?!
Nevertheless, that's only natural.
約束を破ったのは…
君なんだからね。
You broke your promise first.
約束？！
質問に答えろ！
Promise?
Answer my question!
金のかかった悪ふざけしやがって。
てめえは　何もんだ？！
You played this costly evil game...
Who the hell are you?!
The Orpheus Order.
オルペウス・オーダー。
偉大なるオルペウスを信奉し→
We follow the great Orpheus
卑劣なる神々のくびきから
人間を解放せんとする者。
and aim to free humankind from its cowardly gods.
あれは？！
オルペウスの腕輪！　まさか？！
That's an Armband of Orpheus! No way!
フフッ。　僕の名は　フリーセル。
My name is Freecell.
オルペウスリングを持つ　ファイ・ブレインの子供。
I'm a child of the Phi Brain with an Orpheus Ring.
（一同）えっ？！
そんなバカな…！
It can't be...
千枝乃君。
副会長！
Chieno!
Vice President!
大門カイト君　私と戦いなさい。
パズルで。
Daimon Kaito! Fight me...
with a puzzle!
あはっ。
eiyuu kidori itsu datte shinjita muteki no kankaku
I think I'm a hero and believe that I'm invincible.
tatakatte iru no wa chikyuu no tame nanka janai
I'm not fighting for the world.
motto mai peesu de
It's for a more personal,
sou motto shoujikina negai no tame
a more honest wish.
No matter how many times I'm hurt
nando to naku kizutsuite mo